Guide to the H. G. Hotchkiss Essential Oil Company records, 1822-1982.
H. G. Hotchkiss Essential Oil Company records, 1822-1982.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
H. G. Hotchkiss Essential Oil Company records, 1822-1982.
673
H. G. Hotchkiss Essential Oil Company.
94.2 cubic ft.
Accounts, correspondence, banking records, broadsides, prices current, market guides.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes accounts, correspondence, banking records, broadsides, prices current, market guides and other materials relating to the development of the essential oils industry.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Businessman.
Hiram G. Hotchkiss was born in Oneida County, New York, on June 19, 1810. His father, Leman Hotchkiss, moved the family to Phelps, Ontario County, New York, in 1811 and became the pioneer merchant of that region. Upon his death, Hiram and his brother Leman managed the business. After expanding their milling operation, Hiram began to develop an essential oil industry. Hiram moved to Lyons, New York, in 1843, where he began cultivating peppermint, and gradually gained control over the farm supply of mint and over the oil market. Leman remained in Phelps, and carried on his own oil business. Both had general stores, dealt in wheat, flour and produce, and established banks in their respective towns. Hiram became a powerful businessman, controlling prices of western peppermint crops and successfully marketing his product in the United States and Europe. His essential oils garnered many awards, including first prize medals at world's fairs and exhibitions held in England, Germany, America, France and Austria. Hiram Hotchkiss died in 1898, and his sons Calvin and Hiram Jr., took over the business.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes accounts, correspondence, banking records, broadsides, prices current, market guides and other materials relating to the development of the essential oils industry in Lyons, Wayne County, New York, by Hiram G. Hotchkiss and his family. Records give technical details of the essential oil production in the 1860s and 1870s; information as to the prizes awarded them at various fairs and exhibitions held in London, Paris, Vienna, Philadelphia and other cities; and information concerning the organization and administration of these exhibitions, about the awarding of prizes and the effect of these awards on the firms concerned. Accounts and letters document the development of the business, while reports and letters from brokers in New York, Boston and London detail manipulations of the domestic and foreign markets. Included are letters to brokers Taft and Lee in New York City and Myer of Boston that detail financial and credit transactions and market strategies. Also, letters from London, Paris, Rome, Moscow and other European cities discuss trade practices, international prices, the gold flow, shipping information and other business matters.
In addition to oil industry records, the collection includes accounts and letters relating to flour sales (1841-1845) in Indiana and New York by the Hotchkiss agents, Dow & Cary; an agreement between Hotchkiss & Co. with Dow & Cary to build a flour mill at Seneca Falls, N.Y.; deeds, correspondence, and other material relating to lands in Niagara, Ontario and Wayne Counties, and in Michigan; correspondence (1845) relating to Hotchkiss's opposition to proposals made by the Auburn & Rochester Railroad; and correspondence (1850-1858) between Hiram G. and his cousin Calvin Hotchkiss, a banker in Lewiston, regarding the construction of a suspension bridge over the Niagara to Queensborough, the building of a plank road, the use of water power, and the consequent rise of land values; the attitude of Lockport and Buffalo toward building a ship canal around Niagara Falls, the plan for an international bridge, railroad developments, and resulting local, state and national political actions. Included also are letters (1911-1914) relating to the projected Corning, Keuka Lake and Ontario Railroad and to projected changes on the Barge Canal. Account books are primarily oil accounts (1843-1916), but also include daybooks, letter books, mill, flour and meal accounts. Also, three blue bottles used for Hotchkiss essential oils, and medals (14 bronze, 4 silver) awarded to the company at various exhibitions and meetings from 1851 to 1900.
Also, business records, 1952-1982, and files of invoices, 1925-1961, for the company's national and international accounts.
SUBJECTS
Names:
H. G. Hotchkiss Essential Oil Company.; Hotchkiss, Calvin.; Hotchkiss, Hiram G. (Hiram Gilbert), 1810-1897.; Hotchkiss, L. B. (Leman B.); Hotchkiss, Leman.; Hotckkiss, Hiram G.; Auburn & Rochester Railroad.; Dow & Cary.; Taft and Lee.
Subjects:
Bridges--New York (State); Canals--New York (State); Commerce--London.; Commerce--Moscow.; Commerce--Paris.; Commerce--Rome.; Essences and essential oils.; Exhibitions.; Exhibitions--Awards.; Export marketing.; Export sales contracts.; Flour.; Grain--Milling.; Inland water transportation.; Manufactures.; Markets.; Peppermint industry.; Peppermint-oil.; Railroads--New York (State); Real property--Indiana.; Real property--Michigan.; Real property, Exchange of.; Trade routes.; Transportation--Planning.; Industries--New York (State)--Buffalo.; Industries--New York (State)--Lockport.; Industries--New York (State)--Lyons.; Businessmen.
Places:
Niagara County, N.Y.; Oneida County, N.Y.; Ontario County, N.Y.; Phelps (N.Y.); Seneca Falls (N.Y.); Wayne County, N.Y.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.; Broadsides.; Daybooks.; Letter books.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- December 21, 1822-October 31, 1845 (Box 1)
- November 1845-December 1847 (Box 2)
- January 1848-September 1849 (Box 3)
- October 1849-June 1850 (Box 4)
- July 1850-April 1851 (Box 5)
- May 1851-March 1852 (Box 6)
- April 1852-January 1853 (Box 7)
- February 1853-December 1853 (Box 8)
- January 1854-December 1854 (Box 9)
- January 1855-October 1855 (Box 10)
- November 1855-June 1856 (Box 11)
- July 1856-March 1857 (Box 12)
- April 1857-December 1857 (Box 13)
- January 1858-November 1858 (Box 14)
- December 1858-October 1859 (Box 15)
- November 1859-April 1860 (Box 16)
- May 1860-October 1860 (Box 17)
- November 1860-June 1861 (Box 18)
- July 1861-November 1861 (Box 19)
- December 1861-April 1862 (Box 20)
- May 1862-December 1862 (Box 21)
- January 1863-October 1863 (Box 22)
- November 1863-May 1864 (Box 23)
- June 1864-November 1864 (Box 24)
- December 1864-November 1865 (Box 25)
- December 1865-July 1867 (Box 26)
- August 1867-October 1870 (Box 27)
- November 1870-December 1873 (Box 28)
- January 1874-November 1874 (Box 29)
- December 1874-December 1875 (Box 30)
- January 1876-November 1876 (Box 31)
- December 1876-August 24, 1877; November 23, 1877 (Box 32)
- January 1878-1889 (Box 33)
- 1890-November 1895 (Box 34)
- December 1895-September 1896 (Box 35)
- October 1896-February 1897 (Box 36)
- March 1897-September 1897 (Box 37)
- October 1897-April 1898 (Box 38)
- May 1898-December 1898 (Box 39)
- January 1899-October 1899 (Box 40)
- November 1899-October 1900 (Box 41)
- November 1900-December 1901 (Box 42)
- January 1902-August 1903 (Box 43)
- September 1903-May 1904 (Box 44)
- June 1904-December 1905 (Box 45)
- January 1906-July 1907 (Box 46)
- August 1907-December 1908 (Box 47)
- January 1909-September 1910 (Box 48)
- October 1910-October 1911 (Box 49)
- November 1911-December 1912 (Box 50)
- January 1913-December 1913 (Box 51)
- January 1914-December 1915 (Box 52)
- January 1916-December 1921 (Box 53)
- January 1922-April 1926 (Box 54)
- Undated Correspondence (Box 55)
- Undated Correspondence (Box 56)
- Trade cards, advertisements, labels, manuscript volumes, post cards (Box 57)
- Manuscript Volumes (Box 58)
- Serials, newspapers, newspaper clippings, labels (Box 59)
- Printed Material (Box 60)
- A-S, 1931-1933 (Box 61)
- T-Z, 1931-1933; A-N, 1934 (Box 62)
- O-Z, 1934; A-I, 1935-1936 (Box 63)
- J-Z, 1935-1936; A-Z, 1937 (Box 64)
- A-Z, 1938-1940; A-F, 1941-1942 (Box 65)
- G-Z, 1941-1942; A-D, 1943-1945 (Box 66)
- E-Z, 1943-1945; A-Z, 1946 (Box 67)
- A-Z, 1947 (Box 68)
- A-Z, 1948; A-E, 1949 (Box 69)
- F-Z, 1949; A-O, 1950 (Box 70)
- P-Z, 1950; A-Z, 1951; A-Z, 1952 (Box 71)
- A-Z, 1953; A-G, 1954 (Box 72)
- H-Z, 1954; A-F, 1955 (Box 73)
- G-Z, 1955; A-G, 1956 (Box 74)
- H-Z, 1956 (Box 75)
- Medals (Box 76)
- Notebooks and Account Books (14), 1853-1876 (Box 77)
- Lables, Receipts, and Broadsides, 1851-1879 (Box 78)
- H.G. Hotchkiss Wooden Shipping Box (Box 79)
- Invoices, 1915-1927 (Box 80)
- Invoices, 1927-1929 (Box 81)
- Invoices, 1930-1934 (Box 82)
- Invoices, 1935-1942 (Box 83)
- Invoices, 1940-1952 (Box 84)
- Invoices, 1953-1959 (Box 85)
- Invoices, 1960-1972 (Box 86)
- Invoices, 1973-1977 (Box 87)
- Invoices, 1978-1980; 1929-1939 (Box 88)
- Invoices, 1929-1939 (Box 89)
- Buisness Records, 1957 (Box 90)
- Buisness Records, 1958 (Box 91)
- Buisness Records, 1959 (Box 92)
- Buisness Records, 1960 (Box 93)
- Buisness Records, 1961 (Box 94)
- Buisness Records, 1962 (Box 95)
- Buisness Records, 1963 (Box 96)
- Buisness Records, 1964 (Box 97)
- Buisness Records, 1965 (Box 98)
- Buisness Records, 1965-1966 (Box 99)
- Buisness Records, 1967 (Box 100)
- Buisness Records, 1968 (Box 101)
- Buisness Records, 1969 (Box 102)
- Buisness Records, 1970 (Box 103)
- Buisness Records, A-Z, 1971; A-B, 1972 (Box 104)
- Buisness Records, D-Z, 1972; A-B, 1973 (Box 105)
- Buisness Records, D-Z, 1973; A-B, 1974 (Box 106)
- Buisness Records, D-Z, 1974; A-D, 1975 (Box 107)
- Buisness Records, E-Z, 1975; A-H, 1976 (Box 108)
- Buisness Records, I-Z, 1976; A-M, 1977 (Box 109)
- Buisness Records, N-Z, 1977; A-Z, 1978 (Box 110)
- Buisness Records, A-Z, 1979; A-D, 1980 (Box 111)
- Buisness Records, F-Z, 1980; A-I, 1981 (Box 112)
- Buisness Records, L-Z, 1981; A-Z, 1982 (Box 113)
- Miscellany, 1930's-1960's (Box 114)
- Seventy-three volumes on shelf: mostly acct. and ledger books. Few printed books on shelf. In accession folder. (Box 118-123, Volume 1-73)